Council on Foreign Relations Digital Sound Recordings, 1953-1989: Finding Aid MC104.13
Public Policy Papers
- Series 1: Digital Sound Recordings, 1953-1989; 24 boxes
  - Great Britain and the Current International Situation, 1954 October 6; Gifford, Walter S.; Morrison, Herbert, 1888-1965; 1 box (Box 730)
    MC104-29A
  - Collective Security in South Asia, 1954 October 14; Allen, George V. (George Venable), 1903-1970; Dean, Arthur H.; 1 box (Box 730)
    MC104-29B
  - Recent Developments in East Germany, 1954 October 20; Buttenwieser, Benjamin J.; Sullivan, Walter; 1 box (Box 730)
    MC104-30A
  - The Role of Congress in the Conduct of Foreign Relations, 1954 October 26; Finletter, Thomas K. (Thomas Knight), 1893-1980; Fulbright, J. William; 1 box (Box 730)
    MC104-30B
  - European Unity after the London Conference, 1954 October 27; Spaak, Paul-Henri; Spofford, Charles M.; 1 box (Box 730)
    MC104-31A
  - Fresh Impressions of the Paris Conferences, 1954 November 1; Hallstein, Walter; McCloy, John J. (John Jay), 1895-1989; 1 box (Box 730)
    MC104-31B
  - Japanese-American Relations, 1954 November 4; Grew, Joseph C.; Yoshida, Shigeru, 1878-1967; 1 box (Box 730)
    MC104-32A
  - The Problem of Security in Southeast Asia, 1954 November 8; Luce, Henry Robinson, 1898-1967.; Prince Wan Waithayakon; 1 box (Box 730)
    MC104-32B
  - The Gezira Project and Its Significance for the Economic Development of Underdeveloped Regions, 1955 January 17; Gaitskell, Arthur; Hochschild, Walter; 1 box (Box 730)
    MC104-33A
  - Problems of the Foreign Service, 1955 February 23; Saltzman, Charles E. (Charles Eskridge), 1903-1994; Spofford, Charles M.; 1 box (Box 730)
    MC104-33B
    Born digital.; Saltzman, Charles E. (Charles Eskridge), 1903-1994
  - France and the United States, 1955 January 20; Dillon, C. Douglas (Clarence Douglas), 1909-2003; Rockefeller, David, 1915-2017; 1 box (Box 730)
    MC104-34A
  - Turkey and the Defense of the Free World, 1955 January 24; Armstrong, Hamilton Fish, 1893-1973; Gulek, Kasim; 1 box (Box 730)
    MC104-34B
  - Future Prospects of the Coal and Steel Community and of European Economic Integration, 1955 January 31; Altschul, Frank, 1887-1981; Bruce, David K. E., 1898-1977; 1 box (Box 730)
    MC104-35A
  - The Soldier and National Policy, 1955 February 14; McCloy, John J. (John Jay), 1895-1989; Ridgway, Matthew B.; 1 box (Box 730)
    MC104-35B
  - Britain and the United States in the Middle East, 1955 February 24; Bullard, Reader, Sir, 1885-1976; Levy, Walter James, 1911-1997; 1 box (Box 730)
    MC104-36A
  - Problems of the United States Information Service, 1955 March 2; Altschul, Frank, 1887-1981; Streibert, Theodore C.; 1 box (Box 730)
    MC104-36B
  - The Significance of Recent Events in Russia, 1955 March 3; Dallin, David J; Mosely, Philip E. (Philip Edward), 1905-1972; Robinson, Geroid T.; 1 box (Box 730)
    MC104-37A
  - Main Trends in Chinese Communist Political and Economic Policy Since 1949, (China 1), 1955 March 10; Mallory, Walter H. (Walter Hampton), 1892-1980; Rostow, W. W. (Walt Whitman), 1916-2003; 1 box (Box 730)
    MC104-37B
  - Organizing Southeast Asia for Defense Against Communist Agression and Subversion, 1955 March 28; Maffry, August, 1905-; Rivett-Carnac, Douglas C.; 1 box (Box 730)
    MC104-38A
  - The Defensibility of Europe, 1955 March 30; Nicholl, Angus D.; Spofford, Charles M.; 1 box (Box 730)
    MC104-38B
  - Problems of Indian-American Relations, 1955 April 4; Mallory, Walter H. (Walter Hampton), 1892-1980; Mehta, Gaganvihari Lallubhai; 1 box (Box 730)
    MC104-39A
  - United States Foreign Policy in the Far East, 1955 April 7; Nitze, Paul; Robertson, Walter S.; 1 box (Box 730)
    MC104-39B
  - The Prospects for the Southeast Asian Treaty Organization, 1955 April 11; MacArthur, Douglas, 1909-; Stanton, Edwin F.; 1 box (Box 731)
    MC104-40A
  - His Missions to the Middle East Undertaken to Negotiate an Agreement Between the Arab States and Israel for the Joint Development of the Jordan River Valley, 1955 April 13; Gross, Ernest A.; Johnston, Eric; 1 box (Box 731)
    MC104-40B
  - The European Coal and Steel Community, 1955 April 19; Coppe, Albert; Spofford, Charles M.; 1 box (Box 731)
    MC104-41A
  - Egypt: Problems and Prospects, 1955 April 20; Caffery, Jefferson; Josephs, Devereux C.; 1 box (Box 731)
    MC104-41B
  - United States Policy in Latin America, 1955 April 21; Beltrán, Pedro G.; Miller, Edward C.; 1 box (Box 731)
    MC104-42A
  - Reflections on India and Southwest Asia, 1955 April 27; Bowles, Chester, 1901-1986.; Dean, Arthur H.; 1 box (Box 731)
    MC104-42B
  - France's Policy in Europe, 1955 May 16; Armstrong, Hamilton Fish, 1893-1973; Auriol, Vincent, 1884-1966; 1 box (Box 731)
    MC104-43A
  - Problems of Anglo-American Economic Relations, 1955 March 21; Burden, William A. M. (William Armistead Moale), 1906-1984; Viscount Harcourt; 1 box (Box 731)
    MC104-43B
  - The Progress of NATO and the Problems Ahead, 1955 May 25; Hughes, John C.; Spofford, Charles M.; 1 box (Box 731)
    MC104-44A
  - Burma's Foreign and Domestic Policies, 1955 July 5; McCloy, John J. (John Jay), 1895-1989; Nu, U, 1907-1995; 1 box (Box 731)
    MC104-44B
  - American Policy toward the Middle East, 1955 August 26; Dulles, John Foster, 1888-1959.; McCloy, John J. (John Jay), 1895-1989; 1 box (Box 731)
    MC104-45A
    Long dropout and then long period of ambience after introduction, before speech begins. Program ends before question and answer session.
    John Foster Dulles (1888-1959), the fifty-third Secretary of State of the United States for President Dwight D. Eisenhower, had a long and distinguished public career with significant impact upon the formulation of United States foreign policies. He was especially involved with efforts to establish world peace after World War I, the role of the United States in world governance, and Cold War relations between the United States and the Soviet Union.
    Dulles was born on February 25, 1888 in Washington, D.C. to Allen Macy Dulles and Edith Foster. He attended Princeton University, graduating in 1908. During this time, he had his first experience with foreign affairs, serving as secretary to his grandfather, John Watson Foster, during the Second Hague Peace Conference in 1907. After graduation, he studied philosophy and international law for a year at the Sorbonne in Paris, and then attended the George Washington University Law School, earning his LL.B. in 1911. Dulles married Janet Avery on June 26, 1912 and they had two sons, John Walsh and Avery, and one daughter, Lilias Pomeroy (Mrs. Robert Hinshaw).
    After his graduation from law school, Dulles joined the prestigious New York law firm of Sullivan and Cromwell, which specialized in international law. He worked there from 1911 to 1949, rising to become a senior partner. During World War I, Dulles served as assistant to the chairman of the War Trade Board, and then as counsel to the reparations section of the American Commission to Negotiate Peace, and as a member of the American delegation to the Versailles Peace Conference in 1919, serving as Bernard Baruch's chief legal advisor on the Reparations Commission and also serving on the Supreme Economic Council. After returning to Sullivan and Cromwell, he continued to be active in organizations concerned with world affairs, and to express his views on the United States' role in the world through speeches, articles, and the book War, Peace and Change published in 1939. In 1941 he accepted the chairmanship of the Commission to Study the Bases of a Just and Durable Peace, established by the Federal Council of Churches of Christ in America. Dulles presented their "Six Pillars of Peace" plan to President Franklin D. Roosevelt in 1943, as a plan for establishing international cooperation for peace. Throughout his career, Dulles continued to be a prominent lay spokesman for the Protestant church.
    Dulles became increasingly involved in politics at the onset of the Cold War. He represented the United States at the San Francisco organizational conference for the United Nations in 1945, and in many subsequent sessions of the United Nations General Assembly. He served as New York's junior senator from 1949 to 1950, replacing Senator Robert F. Wagner, who resigned due to ill health. Dulles then served as special representative of President Truman, with the rank of ambassador, negotiating the Japanese Peace Treaty of 1951 and the Australian, New Zealand, Philippine and Japanese Security Treaties of 1950-1951. During his negotiations, he observed the growing antagonism between the United States and Soviet Union which subsequently hardened his anti-Communist stance.
    In 1953, President Dwight D. Eisenhower appointed Dulles Secretary of State. His tenure was marked by a close working relationship with the President, staunch anti-Communism, and a philosophy of "collective security" which led to numerous mutual defense treaties. Recognizing that NATO would only provide for the defense of Western Europe, Dulles initiated the Manila Conference in 1954 that resulted in the formation of the Southeast Asian Treaty Organization (SEATO), an agreement between eight nations for the defense of Southeast Asia, and was influential in establishing the 1955 Baghdad Pact for the defense of Turkey, Iraq, Iran, and Pakistan. He was also known for enunciating a policy of "massive retaliation," whereby any attack on U.S. interests anywhere in the world by the Soviet Union or China would be met with an attack on those countries, including the possible use of nuclear weapons.
    Several notable international events marked Dulles's tenure. In 1955, in an effort to induce President Gamal Abdel Nasser of Egypt to support the West, Dulles offered to provide financing for the construction of the Aswan Dam on the Nile River to produce electrical power and for irrigation. However, Dulles withdrew the offer in July 1956 after receiving protests from United States cotton interests and Jewish-Americans, and after Nasser purchased weapons from Czechoslovakia, suggesting he was aligning with the Soviets. Nasser responded by nationalizing the British-owned Suez Canal. Without notifying the United States, Britain, France and Israel invaded Egypt in October 1956 but failed to capture the canal. Dulles condemned the action at the United Nations, and under economic pressure from the United States, the allies withdrew by early 1957.
    Concurrent with the Suez crisis, an uprising in Hungary resulted in the establishment of a new government committed to withdrawing the country from the Warsaw Pact. The Soviets responded with military force, leading the Hungarians to appeal to the United Nations for aid, pleas that were ignored, allowing the Soviets to subsequently crush the revolt and maintain their grip on Eastern Europe.
    In 1958, tensions between Communist China and Taiwan threatened to break out into war when Communist China renewed their shelling of the islands of Jinmen and Mazu and the United States avowed not to appease Mao Zedong. Dulles convinced Taiwan's Chiang Kai-shek to renounce the use of force against mainland China and to withdraw some troops from Jinmen and Mazu, and the Chinese ceased their shelling. Also in 1958, the Soviets threatened to sign a peace treaty with East Germany, terminating the joint occupation of Germany established after World War II, unless a satisfactory agreement was reached within six months. In what would be his last international trip as Secretary of State, Dulles traveled to Europe to reassure Chancellor Konrad Adenauer that the United States would maintain its commitment to West Germany. Eventually, the Soviets agreed to negotiate without a deadline.
    Stricken with cancer, Dulles resigned as Secretary of State in April of 1959. He died on May 24, 1959 in Washington, D.C.
  - Impressions of Soviet Agriculture, 1955 August 30; Altschul, Frank, 1887-1981; Soth, Lauren K.; 1 box (Box 731)
    MC104-45B
    Tape ends abruptly.
  - Fresh Impressions of Russia: 1955, 1955 November 28; Robinson, Geroid T.; Schwartz, Harry; 1 box (Box 731)
    MC104-46
  - Yugoslavia between Two Worlds, 1955 December 1; Armstrong, Hamilton Fish, 1893-1973; Mosely, Philip E. (Philip Edward), 1905-1972; 1 box (Box 731)
    MC104-47A
  - Egypt's Role in the Middle East, 1956 January 30; Byroade, Henry A. (Henry Alfred), 1913-; Josephs, Devereux C.; 1 box (Box 731)
    MC104-47B
  - Pakistan's Foreign Policy with Particular Reference to the Middle East, 1955 December 12; Ali, Mohammed; Johnson, Joseph E. (Joseph Esrey), 1906-1990; 1 box (Box 731)
    MC104-49
  - Recent Political Developments in Brazil, 1956 January 9; Brewer, Samuel Pope; Miller, Warren E. (Warren Edward), 1924-1999; 1 box (Box 731)
    MC104-50A
  - Germany after Geneva, 1956 January 5; Krekeler, Heinz L.; McCloy, John J. (John Jay), 1895-1989; 1 box (Box 731)
    MC104-50B
  - The Foreign Policy of Ireland and Her Relations with the NATO Nations, 1956 March 28; Costello, John A.; McCloy, John J. (John Jay), 1895-1989; 1 box (Box 731)
    MC104-51A
  - Soviet Scientific Capabilities and the West, 1956 March 29; Kelly, Mervin J.; Scoville, Herbert; 1 box (Box 731)
    MC104-51B
  - United States Relations with South Asia: The Challenge of Burma, Pakistan and India, 1956 April 9; Kirk, Grayson L.; McCloy, John J. (John Jay), 1895-1989; 1 box (Box 731)
    MC104-52A
  - The Influence of India in the Former Colonial Belt, (New Challenges in World Politics 3), 1956 April 11; Talbot, Phillips.; Wriston, Henry M. (Henry Merritt), 1889-1978; 1 box (Box 731)
    MC104-52B
  - The Foreseeable Future of Atomic Energy and Mechanical Thought, 1956 April 18; Rabi, Isidor I.; Thomson, George, 1903-1987.; 1 box (Box 732)
    MC104-53
  - Turkey: Cornerstone of Middle East Defense, 1956 April 24; Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich), 1908-1979; Warren, Avra Milvin, 1893-1957; 1 box (Box 732)
    MC104-54A
  - Soviet Education, Its Program and Challenge, 1956 April 26; Benton, William, 1900-1973.; Kirk, Grayson L.; 1 box (Box 732)
    MC104-54B
  - United States Economic Aid Programs, (New Challenges in World Politics II 1), 1956 May 8; Cleveland, Harlan; Wriston, Henry M. (Henry Merritt), 1889-1978; 1 box (Box 732)
    MC104-55B
    Program contains an initial introduction which is cut off; the second introduction fits with the rest of the meeting.
    Harlan Cleveland (1918-2008) was a public administrator, ambassador to NATO, and a political scientist. He served in several positions related to the administration of economic aid programs during the 1940s, as an assistant secretary in the State Department and as U.S. ambassador to NATO during the 1960s, and also held positions at three universities and the Aspen Institute. Cleveland began his career in public service in 1940 as a writer in the information division of the Farm Security Administration. In 1942, he embarked on a period of work with economic aid, first with the Board of Economic Warfare (later the Foreign Economic Administration) from 1942 to 1944, where he focused on problems of relief and economic rehabilitation of the European countries that were occupied by Germany. He next served as executive director and acting vice president of the economic section of the Allied Control Commission in Rome from 1944 to 1946. Cleveland worked for the United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration (UNRRA) as department chief of the Italian Mission from 1946 to 1947 and as director of the China office from 1947 to 1948. He then served as director (1948-1949) and department assistant administrator (1949-1951) of the Far East Program Division of the ECA (Economic Cooperation Administration). His final position during this period of his career was assistant director for the Mutual Security Agency, in charge of the European program, from 1952 to 1953, when he supervised the fourth year of the Marshall Plan. Cleveland left government service in 1953 to become executive editor of The Reporter, a liberal biweekly magazine in New York City, a position he held until 1956. He also served as the publisher from 1955 to 1956. From 1956 to 1961, he was a professor of political science and dean of the Maxwell Graduate School of Citizenship and Public Affairs at Syracuse University, where he built a significant overseas training program. In 1961, President John F. Kennedy appointed Cleveland assistant secretary for international organization affairs in the U.S. Department of State, a position he held until 1965. In this position, he served as an intermediary between Secretary of State Dean Rusk and U.S. ambassador to the United Nations Adlai Stevenson and was involved in responding to several peace and security crises during that period, including in the Congo, West New Guinea, Cypress, the Middle East, and the Cuban missile crisis. He was also responsible for ensuring that ambassadors to international organizations promoted and protected U.S. interests and for selecting the U.S. delegation for any international projects or conferences. Cleveland then served President Lyndon B. Johnson as U.S. ambassador to NATO (North Atlantic Treaty Organization) from 1965 to 1969. Cleveland advocated nuclear arms control and strengthening the United Nations for an expanded peace-keeping role. He also organized the move of NATO from Paris to Brussels when French president Charles de Gaulle removed France from the alliance in 1966. Cleveland returned to academia in 1969 as the eighth president of the University of Hawaii, a position he held until 1974. As president, he oversaw the expansion of the university to include a medical school, law school, and an international astronomy project. From 1974 to 1980, he was director of the program in international affairs of the Aspen Institute for Humanistic Studies, located in Princeton, New Jersey. The program was one of six "think tanks" operated by the Institute at that time, each considering a significant issue. The programs developed ideas and proposals for adapting existing institutions and developing new ones to address the issues. During his tenure, the international affairs program focused on methods for coping with an increasingly interdependent world, including the need for a new international economic order. In the last change of his career, Cleveland served as the first dean of the Hubert H. Humphrey Institute of Public Affairs at the University of Minnesota from 1980 to 1987. After his retirement, Cleveland continued to write and lecture on a wide variety of topics, largely within the fields of leadership, public policy and world affairs. His books include The Overseas Americans (1960), The Promise of World Tensions (1961), The Obligations of Power: American Diplomacy in the Search for Peace (1966), The Future Executive (1972), and The Knowledge Executive (1985). Harlan Cleveland was born in New York City on January 19, 1918 to Stanley and Marian (Van Buren) Cleveland. He graduated from Princeton University in 1938, where he studied politics, and then studied for a year at Oxford University as a Rhodes Scholar. He married Lois W. Burton on July 12, 1941 and they had three children: Melantha, Zoe, and Alan. Cleveland died on May 30, 2008 at the age of 90.
  - British Strategy in the Middle East, 1956 May 10; Altschul, Frank, 1887-1981; Peck, John H.; 1 box (Box 732)
    MC104-56A
  - Building a National Defense Program, 1956 May 14; McCloy, John J. (John Jay), 1895-1989; Taylor, Maxwell D. (Maxwell Davenport), 1901-1987; 1 box (Box 732)
    MC104-56B
  - Our Western Alliance, 1956 May 18; Dewey, Thomas E. (Thomas Edmund), 1902-1971; Gaitskell, Hugh, 1906-1963; 1 box (Box 732)
    MC104-57A
  - The Effect of Air Power on NATO and Western Europe, 1956 May 21; Darvall, Lawrence; Spofford, Charles M.; 1 box (Box 732)
    MC104-57B
  - American Information Programs, (New Challenges in World Politics 3), 1956 May 28; Barrett, Edward W. (Edward Ware), 1910-1989; Wriston, Henry M. (Henry Merritt), 1889-1978; 1 box (Box 732)
    MC104-58
  - The Significance of Recent Soviet Events, 1956 June 14; Adenauer, Konrad, 1876-1967.; McCloy, John J. (John Jay), 1895-1989; 1 box (Box 732)
    MC104-59A
  - Comments on a European Trip, 1956 July 5; McCloy, John J. (John Jay), 1895-1989; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972.; 1 box (Box 732)
    MC104-60
  - A British Estimate of Communist China, 1956 September 17; Dean, Arthur H.; Grantham, Alexander, 1899-1978; 1 box (Box 732)
    MC104-61A
  - Indian Policy and the Suez Crisis, 1956 September 20; Armstrong, Hamilton Fish, 1893-1973; Moraes, Frank; 1 box (Box 732)
    MC104-61B
  - Personal Impressions of Russia, Summer 1956, 1956 September 26; Hazard, John N.; Mosely, Philip E. (Philip Edward), 1905-1972; 1 box (Box 732)
    MC104-62A
  - A Critique of United States Policy in Latin America, 1956 October 16; Beltrán, Pedro G.; Rockefeller, David, 1915-2017; 1 box (Box 732)
    MC104-62B
  - The Suez Canal and French Policy, 1956 October 22; Alphand, Hervé; Bruce, David K. E., 1898-1977; 1 box (Box 732)
    MC104-63A
  - The Tragedy in Hungary, 1956 November 7; Cherne, Leo, 1912-1999; Mosely, Philip E. (Philip Edward), 1905-1972; 1 box (Box 732)
    MC104-63B
  - The Tragedy in Hungary, 1956 November 7; Cherne, Leo, 1912-1999; Mosely, Philip E. (Philip Edward), 1905-1972; 1 box (Box 732)
    MC104-64
  - The Present Situation, 1956 November 16; Spaak, Paul-Henri; Spofford, Charles M.; 1 box (Box 732)
    MC104-65A
  - Observations on Eastern Europe, 1956 November 19; Johnston, Eric; 1 box (Box 732)
    MC104-65B
    Introduction is cut off.
  - United States Policies in the Middle East, 1956 November 20; Gross, Ernest A.; Russell, Francis; 1 box (Box 733)
    MC104-66A
  - Australia Looks at Suez: A Commonwealth View, 1956 November 26; Casey, Richard G.; Josephs, Devereux C.; 1 box (Box 733)
    MC104-66B
  - The Future of NATO, 1956 November 27; Lange, Halvard Manthey, 1902-1970; Spofford, Charles M.; 1 box (Box 733)
    MC104-67A
  - Problems Facing New Tunisia, 1956 November 24; Bourguiba, Habib, 1903-2000; Rockefeller, David, 1915-2017; 1 box (Box 733)
    MC104-67B
    Speech in French.
  - Indonesian Policy and the World Crisis, 1956 November 30; Abdulgani, Roeslan, 1914-; Prioleau, Horry F.; 1 box (Box 733)
    MC104-68A
  - A Fresh look at NATO, 1956 December 3; Gordon, Lincoln; Hughes, John C.; 1 box (Box 733)
    MC104-68B
  - Egyptian Policies in the Middle East, 1956 December 11; Fawzi, Mahmoud; Reed, Philip D.; 1 box (Box 733)
    MC104-69A
  - The Arab States and the Baghdad Pact, 1956 December 17; Al-Jamali, Mohamed Fadhil; Rockefeller, David, 1915-2017; 1 box (Box 733)
    MC104-69B
  - The State of the NATO Alliance: The Recent Council Meeting, 1956 December 27; Bowie, Robert R., (Robert Richardson) 1909-2013; Hughes, John C.; 1 box (Box 733)
    MC104-70A
  - 1957 - Problems of United States' Foreign Policy, 1957 January 3; Kennan, George F. (George Frost), 1904-2005; Kirk, Grayson L.; 1 box (Box 733)
    MC104-70B
  - Italy and the European Situation, 1957 January 8; Bunker, Ellsworth, 1894-1984; Luce, Clare Boothe, 1903-1987; 1 box (Box 733)
    MC104-71A
  - The United States Role in the Middle East, 1957 January 14; Armstrong, Hamilton Fish, 1893-1973; Hoskins, Harold B.; 1 box (Box 733)
    MC104-71B
    Harold Boies Hoskins was a businessman, diplomat, and educator working in Middle
    Eastern affairs. Born in Beirut and raised by American missionary parents, he
    graduated from Hill School in 1913 and Princeton in 1917. Hoskins served in both WWI
    and II, and in 1942, he was commissioned by President Roosevelt to act as a U.S.
    diplomatic emissary in Palestine. He became a special assistant to the U.S.
    ambassador in Tehran in 1944, and served as a counselor for economic affairs at the